Finding Aid for the Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps Records, 1938-1940
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps Records, 1938-1940
Mus. Arc. 61
Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps
1 box ( 24 folders, 3 black and white photographs )
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The records of Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps include meeting minutes, its constitution and bylaws, business correspondence, and three black and white photographs.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Irene (Montz) Phillips, 2012.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
The photographs have been digitized and are linked from the container list.
Historical Note
Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps was established in June 1938 as successor to the Martha Washington Drum Corps. The minutes of the meeting on May 2 1938 state the name of the organization as the Martha Washington Drum Corps with the president being Mrs. Von Volkenburg and the drum major Hilda Schieder. The minutes of the next meeting on June 27 1938 state that the president has changed to Hilda Schieder and that the Martha Washington Drum Corps has been disbanded. A vote was taken at that meeting on the name of the new organization and it became known as Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps. The name is stated in variant forms elsewhere in the minutes and constitution, including Hilda Schieder Drum Corps and Hilda Schieder's Fife & Drum Corps. However, it is clearly named Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps under Section 1 of the By-laws and identified as such on the logos on the drum heads in the photographs.
Not much biographical information has been discovered about Hilda Schieder. The Telephone list in the collection shows her living at 144 Wohlers Avenue, Buffalo, New York. There is a reference to her being the director of the Martha Washington Drum Corps in the August 19 1935 issue of the Lockport New York Union Sun and Journal newspaper. According to a Buffalo Courier Express article (Monday, March 14, 1966) Hilda Schieder was struck by a car and killed while crossing Kenmore Avenue at Hobmoor Avenue March 13, 1966. She was reportedly about 60 years of age and living in Williamsville at the time of the accident. She was born Hildegard Kraus, daughter of Frank and Anna Kraus.
Scope and Content Note
The records of Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps include meeting minutes, its constitution and bylaws, business correspondence, and three black and white photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
I. Organization documents
II. Correspondence
III. Meeting minutes
IV. Photographs
Container List
- Organization documents, 1938-1939, I.; Folder 1-3
  Arranged in order of significance.
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Constitution and By-laws, 6 February 1939, 9 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 01)
  - Attendance at business meetings, 19 September 1938-5 June 1939, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Folder 02)
  - Telephone list with street addresses of members of Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps, undated, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Folder 03)
- Correspondence, 1940, II.; Folder 4-10
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - American Legion. Adam Plewacki Post No. 799 (Buffalo, N.Y.): Letter from Edward B. Nowak on behalf of the Adam Plewacki Post No. 799 to Hilda Schieder Drum Corps, 13 April 1940, 1 typescript leaf; Invitation to participate in Flag Day event in the Buffalo Civic Stadium 14 June 1940. Accompanied by pre-addressed postcard to accept the invitation. (Box 1, Folder 04)
  - American Legion. Buffalo Drum Corps (Buffalo, N.Y.): Letter from Lee Suttell on behalf of the Buffalo Drum Corps (American Legion) to Hilda Schieder's Drum and Bugle Corps, 14 March 1940, 2 typescript leaves; Mimeograph copy of invitation to participate in an event at Buffalo Civic Stadium 30 May 1940. (Box 1, Folder 05)
  - Ladie's Auxiliary Patrol of the Woodlawn Fire Department (Lackawanna, N.Y.): Letter from Mrs. D. Brown on behalf of the Ladie's Auxiliary Patrol of the Woodlawn Fire Department to Martha Washington Drum Corps, 1940, 2 typescript leaves; Invitation to attendance at the Patrol's Field Day, June 1 of unknown year. Date from Minutes of 27 May 1940. (Box 1, Folder 06)
  - Lake Shore Volunteer Fire Co. (Hamburg, N.Y.): Postcard from Lake Shore Volunteer Fire Co. to Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps, 11 May 1940, 1 typescript leaf; Invitation and attached acceptance form for Field day and parade 22-23 June. (Box 1, Folder 07)
  - Moose-Legion Drum Corps (Lancaster, N.Y.): Postcard from Moose-Legion Drum Corps to Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps, 10 May 1940, 1 typescript leaf; Notice about Carnival event 3-8 June 1940 and parade 7 June 1940. (Box 1, Folder 08)
  - Rescue Volunteer Hose Co. No. 1 (Cheektowaga, N.Y.): Letter from Rescue Volunteer Hose Co. No. 1, 1940, 1 typescript leaf; Form letter invitation to participate in the company's parade on 28 June [1940] (date from perpetual calendar) Accompanied by pre-addressed postcard to accept the invitation. (Box 1, Folder 09)
  - Union Fire Company (Gardenville, N.Y.): Letter from the Union Fire Company, 6 May 1940, 1 typescript leaf; Form letter invitation to attend the annual Field day and parade Sunday 2 June 1940. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Meeting minutes, 1938-1940, III.; Folder 11-24
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Martha Washington Drum Corps (Buffalo, N.Y.): Meeting minutes, 2 May 1938, 1 manuscript leaf; Minutes for the Martha Washington Drum Corps, directed by Mrs. Van Volkenburg, drum major Hilda Schieder. Notes recorded by Anna Miller. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Martha Washington Drum Corps (Buffalo, N.Y.): Meeting minutes, 27 June 1938, 2 manuscript leaves; The new name of the corps, Hilda Schieder Drum Corps, was adopted by vote. Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 22 August 1938, 2 typescript leaves; Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 19 September 1938, 2 manuscript leaves; Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 17 October 1938, 2 manuscript leaves; Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 21 November 1938, 4 manuscript leaves; Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 5 December 1938, 1 manuscript leaf; Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 6 February 1939, 3 manuscript leaves; Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 20 March 1939, 3 manuscript leaves; Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 3 April 1939, 3 manuscript leaves; Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 5 June 1939, 3 manuscript leaves; Marked June 3 on the first page and June 5 on the following pages. Notes recorded by Anna E. Hirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 1 March 1940, 2 manuscript leaves and 2 typescript leaves; Notes recorded by Irene E. Montz in pencil draft and typescript with revisions. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 27 May 1940, 2 typescript leaves; Notes recorded by Irene E. Montz. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps: Meeting minutes, 17 June 1940, 1 manuscript leaf and 1 typescript leaf; Notes recorded by Irene E. Montz. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Photographs, 1938, IV.; Folder 25-27
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps group portrait, 26 July 1938, 1 black and white photograph; 13 x 18 cm.; Identified in the photograph are Irene Montz (with glockenspiel (bell lyre), first on left in bottom row), Hilda Schieder (standing center in dark uniform between two bass drums), and Clara Montz (fourth person to right of Hilda Schieder, with dark uniform and shoulder straps). To the left rear of Schieder, in the white dress and black feathered hat, is Ann Wirtzel. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hilda Schieder's Drum Corps group portrait at German Day, 14 August 1938, 1 black and white photograph; 9 x 13 cm.; Identified in the photograph are Irene Montz (first person on left, holding glockenspiel (bell lyre)) and Hilda Schieder (center, in white uniform). Date confirmed from Minutes of 27 June 1938. Accompanied by photocopy of the two group photographs with Hilda Schieder, Irene Montz, and Clara Montz identified. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hilda Schieder sitting at a desk, undated, 1 black and white photograph; 9 x 13 cm. (Box 1, Folder 27)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Schieder, Hilda; Martha Washington Drum Corps (Buffalo, N.Y.)
Subjects
Women musicians--New York (State)--Buffalo; Fife and drum corps--New York (State)--Buffalo; Women--Societies and clubs--New York (State)--Buffalo
Genres
Minutes; Bylaws (administrative records); Black-and-white photographs; Correspondence